I'm going to talk about the power of a word:
سأتحدث عن قوة كلمة:
jihad.
الجهاد
To the vast majority of practicing Muslims,
بالنسبة للغالبية العظمى من المسلمين المتدينين،
jihad is an internal struggle for the faith.
الجهاد هو نضال داخلى للإيمان
It is a struggle within, a struggle against vice, sin,
هو صراع مع النفس، نضال ضد السوء والخطيئة
temptation, lust, greed.
والاغراء و الشهوة و الجشع.
It is a struggle to try and live a life
هو نضال لتحاول و لتعيش حياة
that is set by the moral codes written in the Koran.
تحكمها القواعد الاخلاقية المذكورة في القرآن.
In that original idea, the concept of jihad is as important
في هذه الفكرة الأساسية، مفهوم الجهاد هو مهم
to Muslims as the idea of grace is to Christians.
للمسلمين كأهمية فكرة العفو في المسيحية.
It's a very powerful word, jihad, if you look at it in that respect,
من ذلك المنظور فإن "جهاد" كلمة قوية،
and there's a certain almost mystical resonance to it.
ولها نوع من الصدى الروحاني.
And that's the reason why, for hundreds of years,
وهذا هو السبب، أنه ولمئات السنين،
Muslims everywhere have named their children Jihad,
كان المسلمين في كل مكان يسمون أبنائهم جهاد،
their daughters as much as their sons, in the same way
بنات وبنين، بنفس الطريقة
that, say, Christians name their daughters Grace,
التي، يسمي بها المسيحيون بناتهم غريس،
and Hindus, my people, name our daughters Bhakti,
والهندوس، شعبي، يسمون بناتنا بهاكتي،
which means, in Sanskrit, spiritual worship.
والتي تعني في السنسكريتية، العبادة الروحية.
But there have always been, in Islam, a small group,
لكن كان هناك دائما في الإسلام، مجموعة صغيرة،
a minority, who believe that jihad
أقلية تعتقد أن الجهاد
is not only an internal struggle but also an external struggle
ليس فقط مجاهدة داخلية ولكنه أيضا خارجي
against forces that would threaten the faith, or the faithul.
ضد القوى التي قد تهدد الدين، أو المؤمنين
And some of these people believe that in that struggle,
وبعض هؤلاء يعتقدون بأن في هذه المجاهدة،
it is sometimes okay to take up arms.
لا بأس من حمل السلاح أحيانا.
And so the thousands of young Muslim men
وبالتالي فإن آلاف الشبان المسلمين
who flocked to Afghanistan in the 1980s
الذين تدفقوا نحو أفغنستان في الثمانينات
to fight against the Soviet occupation of a Muslim country,
لقتال الاحتلال السوفياتي لبلد مسلم،
in their minds they were fighting a jihad,
في اعتقادهم كان قتالهم جهاداً،
they were doing jihad,
كانوا يجاهدون،
and they named themselves the Mujahideen,
وسموا أنفسهم بالمجاهدين،
which is a word that comes from the same root as jihad.
الكلمة التي اشتقت من نفس جذر كلمة جهاد.
And we forget this now, but back then
وقد نسينا ذلك اليوم، لكن بالعودة إلى ذلك الوقت
the Mujahideen were celebrated in this country, in America.
آنذاك فقد احتفل بالمجاهدين في ذلك البلد، في أمريكا.
We thought of them as holy warriors who were taking
كنا نعتبرهم كالمحاربين المقدسين الذين حملوا
the good fight to the ungodly communists.
راية الحرب المقدسة ضد الفجار الاشتراكيين
America gave them weapons, gave them money,
أعطتهم أمريكا الأسلحة، والمال،
gave them support, encouragement.
والدعم، والتشجيع.
But within that group, a tiny, smaller group,
لكن داخل المجموعة، قلة، مجموعة صغيرة،
a minority within a minority within a minority,
أقلية داخل أقلية الأقلية
were coming up with a new and dangerous
ستتكون مع مفهوم جديد
conception of jihad,
وخطير للجهاد،
and in time this group would come to be led by Osama bin Laden,
وبمرور الوقت هذه المجموعة ستتم قيادتها من طرف أسامة بن لادن،
and he refined the idea.
و قد أعاد تعريف الفكرة
His idea of jihad was a global war of terror,
كانت فكرته عن الجهاد تقضي بالحرب الشاملة من الإرهاب،
primarily targeted at the far enemy,
استهدف في البداية العدو البعيد،
at the crusaders from the West, against America.
الصليبيين من الغرب، ضد أمريكا.
And the things he did in the pursuit of this jihad
والأمور التي فعلها لمواصلة الجهاد
were so horrendous, so monstrous,
كانت وحشية جداً و رهيبة جداً
and had such great impact,
وكان لها أثراً كبيراً
that his definition was the one that stuck,
حتى أن تعريفه هو الذي التصق وبقي
not just here in the West.
ليس فقط هنا في الغرب .
We didn't know any better. We didn't pause to ask.
لم نكن نعرف أكثر من ذلك ، و لم نقف لنسأل .
We just assumed that if this insane man and his psychopathic followers
افترضنا إن كان هذا الإنسان غير العاقل و تابعيه ذوي المشاكل النفسية
were calling what they did jihad, then that's what jihad must mean.
يطلقون على ما يفعلون جهاد، إذاً فلا بد أن هذا ما يعنيه الجهاد
But it wasn't just us. Even in the Muslim world,
و لكن ليس فقط نحن، حتى في العالم المسلم
his definition of jihad began to gain acceptance.
تعريفه للجهاد بدأ يلقى قبولاً
A year ago I was in Tunis, and I met the imam
منذ عام مضى كنت في تونس، و قابلت إماماً
of a very small mosque, an old man.
لجامع صغير، رجل مسن
Fifteen years ago, he named his granddaughter Jihad,
قبل 15 عاماً مضت، أطلق على حفيدته اسم جهاد
after the old meaning. He hoped that a name like that
كما في التعريف القديم، و قد كان يأمل أن اسم كهذا
would inspire her to live a spiritual life.
سيلهمها لتعيش حياة روحية
But he told me that after 9/11,
و قد أخبرني أنه بعد 9/11
he began to have second thoughts.
بدأ يعيد التفكير
He worried that if he called her by that name,
أحس بالقلق أنه إذا دعاها بهذا الاسم
especially outdoors, outside in public,
خصوصاً خارج المنزل، في الخارج أمام الناس
he might be seen as endorsing bin Laden's idea of jihad.
سيبدو كأنه يؤيد فكرة بن لادن عن الجهاد
On Fridays in his mosque, he gave sermons
في يوم الجمعة في مسجده، يلقي الخطبة
trying to reclaim the meaning of the word,
محاولاً أن يستعيد معنى الكلمة
but his congregants, the people who came to his mosque,
و لكن المصلين الذين يحضرون إلى مسجده
they had seen the videos. They had seen pictures
قد شاهدوا الفيديو.. قد شاهدوا الصور
of the planes going into the towers, the towers coming down.
للطائرتين تصطدمان بالأبراج، و الأبراج تتهاوى
They had heard bin Laden say that that was jihad,
و قد سمعوا بن لادن يقول أن هذا هو الجهاد،
and claimed victory for it. And so the old imam worried
و يدعي النصر باسمه. مما سبب القلق للإمام الشيخ
that his words were falling on deaf ears. No one was paying attention.
أن كلماته كانت تلاقي آذاناً صماء، لم يلق له أحداً بالاً
He was wrong. Some people were paying attention,
و قد كان على خطأ، بعض الناس كانوا منتبهين
but for the wrong reasons.
و لكن للأسباب الخطأ
The United States, at this point, was putting pressure
الولايات المتحدة، في هذه اللحظة، كانت تضغط
on all its Arab allies, including Tunisia,
على حلفائها العرب، بما فيهم تونس
to stamp out extremism in their societies,
لترفض التطرف في مجتمعاتها
and this imam found himself suddenly in the crosshairs
و هذا الإمام وجد نفسه فجأة في تقاطع
of the Tunisian intelligence service.
مع جهاز المخابرات التونسي
They had never paid him any attention before --
الذي لم يلق إليه بالاً من قبل
old man, small mosque --
رجل عجوز، مسجد صغير --
but now they began to pay visits,
و لكنهم بدأوا بزيارته الآن
and sometimes they would drag him in for questions,
و أحيانا جروه ليحيب عن الأسئلة
and always the same question:
و دائماً نفس السؤال:
"Why did you name your granddaughter Jihad?
"لماذا أسميت حفيدتك جهاد؟"
Why do you keep using the word jihad in your Friday sermons?
لماذا تستعمل الكلمة جهاد في خطبة الجمعة؟
Do you hate Americans?
هل تكره الأمريكان؟
What is your connection to Osama bin Laden?"
ما صلتك بأسامة بن لادن؟
So to the Tunisian intelligence agency,
لأن بالنسبة لجهاز المخابرات التونسي
and organizations like it all over the Arab world,
و الأجهزة الشبيهة له في كل أنحاء العالم العربي
jihad equaled extremism,
كلمة الجهاد تعني التطرف
Bin Laden's definition had become institutionalized.
تم التأسيس لتعريف بن لادن
That was the power of that word that he was able to do.
هذه كانت قوة الكلمة التي استطاع أن يصنعها
And it filled this old imam, it filled him with great sadness.
و قد ملأت نفس هذا الإمام الشيخ، ملأتها بحزن عظيم
He told me that, of bin Laden's many crimes, this was,
و قد أخبرني أن من بين جرائم بن لادن المتعددة، هذه
in his mind, one that didn't get enough attention,
في رأيه لم تلق اهتماماً كفاية
that he took this word, this beautiful idea.
أنه قد أخذ هذه الكلمة، هذه الفكرة الجميلة
He didn't so much appropriate it as kidnapped it
أخذها عنوة، اختطفها
and debased it and corrupted it
و لوثها، افسدها
and turned it into something it was never meant to be,
و حولها إلى شيء لم تعنه من قبل أبداً
and then persuaded all of us that it always was
ثم أقنعنا جميعاً أن هذا ما كان
a global jihad.
الجهاد العالمي
But the good news is
و لكن الخبر الجيد هو
that the global jihad is almost over, as bin Laden defined it.
أن الجهاد العالمي كما عرفه بن لادن قد انتهى تقريباً،
It was dying well before he did,
لقد بدأ يموت حتى قبل موته
and now it's on its last legs.
و الآن هو في الرمق الأخير
Opinion polls from all over the Muslim world show
استطلاعات الرأي في كل العالم الإسلامي أوضحت
that there is very little interest among Muslims
أن هنالك اهتمام قليل جداً بين المسلمين
in a global holy war against the West,
في الحرب العالمية المقدسة ضد الغرب
against the far enemy.
ضد العدو البعيد
The supply of young men willing to fight and die for this cause is dwindling.
أعداد الشباب المستعدين للقتال و الموت من أجل هذه القضية تتناقص
The supply of money — just as important, more important perhaps —
الأموال الممنوحة - مماثلة للأهمية أو ربما أهم -
the supply of money to this activity is also dwindling.
الأموال الممنوحة لهذا النشاط أيضا تتناقص
The wealthy fanatics who were previously
المتعصبين الأثرياء الذين كانوا سابقاً
sponsoring this kind of activity are now less generous.
يرعون هذا النوع من النشاط الآن أصبحوا أقل كرماً
What does that mean for us in the West?
ماذا يعني هذا بالنسبة لنا في الغرب؟
Does it mean we can break out the champagne,
هل يعني أن نحتفل
wash our hands of it, disengage, sleep easy at night?
و نغسل أيدينا منه، ننسحب من المعركة، ننام ليلاً قريري الأعين؟
No. Disengagement is not an option,
لا. الانسحاب ليس خيار،
because if you let local jihad survive,
لأنه إذا نجا الجهاد المحلي،
it becomes international jihad.
سيتحول إلى جهاد عالمي.
And so there's now a lot of different
و بالتالي هناك الآن كثير من الاختلافات
violent jihads all over the world.
الجهاد العنيف في كل أنحاء العالم.
In Somalia, in Mali, in Nigeria,
في الصومال، في مالي، في نيجيريا،
in Iraq, in Afghanistan, Pakistan, there are groups that claim
في العراق، في أفغاستان، باكستان، هناك مجموعات تدعي
to be the inheritors of the legacy of Osama bin Laden.
بأنها ورثة ميراث أسامة بن لادن.
They use his rhetoric.
إنهم يستخدمون نفس خطابته
They even use the brand name he created for his jihad.
إنهم حتى يستخدمون الاسم الذي اخترعه لجهاده
So there is now an al Qaeda in the Islamic Maghreb,
و بالتالي توجد الآن "القاعدة" في المغرب الإسلامي
there's an al Qaeda in the Arabian Peninsula,
و توجد القاعدة في شبه الجزيرة العربية
there is an al Qaeda in Mesopotamia.
و توجد القاعدة في بلاد ما بين النهرين
There are other groups -- in Nigeria, Boko Haram,
و توجد جماعات أخرى -- في نيجيريا، بوكو حرام
in Somalia, al Shabaab -- and they all pay homage to Osama bin Laden.
في الصومال، الشباب-- و جميعها قدمت البيعة لأسامة بن لادن
But if you look closely,
و لكن إذا نظرنا عن قرب،
they're not fighting a global jihad.
إنهم لا يحاربون في جهاد عالمي
They're fighting battles over much narrower issues.
إنهم يحاربون في معارك لأجل قضايا أضيق.
Usually it has to do with ethnicity or race or sectarianism,
عادة تكون على علاقة بالعرق أو السلالة أو الطائفية،
or it's a power struggle.
أو تكون صراع قوة.
More often than not, it's a power struggle
في الغالب الأعم، هو صراع قوة
in one country, or even a small region within one country.
في بلد ما أو حتى في منطقة من هذا البلد.
Occasionally they will go across a border,
في بعض الأحيان يعبرون الحدود،
from Iraq to Syria, from Mali to Algeria,
من العراق إلى سوريا، من مالي إلى الجزائر،
from Somalia to Kenya, but they're not fighting
من الصومال إلى كينيا، و لكنهم لا يحاربون
a global jihad against some far enemy.
في جهاد عالمي ضد عدو بعيد
But that doesn't mean
و لكن هذا لا يعني
that we can relax.
أن بإمكاننا أن نسترخي.
I was in Yemen recently, where -- it's the home
زرت اليمن مؤخراً، حيث --
of the last al Qaeda franchise
آخر معاقل القاعدة
that still aspires to attack America, attack the West.
ما زالت تطمح في أن تهاجم أمريكا، تهاجم الغرب.
It's old school al Qaeda.
إنها مدرسة القاعدة القديمة
You may remember these guys.
قد تتذكرون هؤلاء الأشخاص
They are the ones who tried to send the underwear bomber here,
إنهم الذين حاولوا أن يرسلوا المفجر الانتحاري إلى هنا،
and they were using the Internet to try and instigate
و كانوا يستخدمون الانترنت لتشجيع
violence among American Muslims.
العنف بين المسلمين الأمريكان
But they have been distracted recently.
و لكن انتباههم قد تشتت مؤخراً
Last year, they took control over a portion of southern Yemen,
العام الماضي، استلموا السلطة في جزء من اليمن الجنوبي
and ran it, Taliban-style.
و أداروهو على نمط طالبان
And then the Yemeni military got its act together,
مما حفز الجيش اليمني على أن يلملم أطرافه ليتحرك
and ordinary people rose up against these guys
و ناهض الناس العاديون هؤلاء الأشخاص
and drove them out, and since then, most of their activities,
و دحروهم خارجاً، و منذ ذلك الحين، معظم أنشطتهم
most of their attacks have been directed at Yemenis.
معظم هجماتهم تم توجيهها لليمنيين.
So I think we've come to a point now where we can say
إذا أعتقد أننا قد وصلنا إلى نقطة حيث يمكننا أن نقول
that, just like all politics, all jihad is local.
أن، مثل كل السياسيين، كل الجهاد محلي.
But that's still not reason for us to disengage,
و لكن هذا ما زال ليس سبب يدعونا إلى الانسحاب
because we've seen that movie before, in Afghanistan.
لأننا شاهدنا هذا الفيلم من قبل، في أفغانستان
When those Mujahideen defeated the Soviet Union,
عندما هزم هؤلاء المجاهدين الاتحاد السوفييتي
we disengaged.
انسحبنا
And even before the fizz had gone out of our celebratory champagne,
و قبل أن نكمل احتفالنا
the Taliban had taken over in Kabul,
استولت طالبان على كابول
and we said, "Local jihad, not our problem."
و قلنا "جهاد محلي، ليست مشكلتنا"
And then the Taliban gave the keys of Kandahar
ثم أعطت طالبان مفاتيح قندهار
to Osama bin Laden. He made it our problem.
لأسامة بن لادن الذي جعله مشكلتنا
Local jihad, if you ignore it, becomes global jihad again.
الجهاد المحلي، إذا تجاهلناه سيتحول إلى جهاد عالمي مجددأً
The good news is that it doesn't have to be.
الأخبار الجيدة أنه ليس هذا ما يجب أن يحدث
We know how to fight it now.
نحن نعلم كيف نحاربه الآن
We have the tools. We have the knowhow,
نحن نملك الأدوات، نحن نملك المعرفة
and we can take the lessons we've learned
و يمكننا أن نستصحب الدروس التي تعلمناها
from the fight against global jihad, the victory against global jihad,
من القتال ضد الجهاد العالمي، النصر ضد الجهاد العالمي
and apply those to local jihad.
و نطبق ذلك على الجهاد المحلي
What are those lessons? We know who killed bin Laden:
ما هي تلك الدروس؟ نحن نعلم من قتل بن لادن:
SEAL Team Six.
الفريق سييل 6.
Do we know, do we understand, who killed bin Ladenism?
هل نعلم، هل نفهم من قتل حركة بن لادن؟
Who ended the global jihad?
من قضى على الجهاد العالمي؟
There lie the answers to the solution to local jihad.
هناك تقبع الإجابات لحل الجهاد المحلي
Who killed bin Ladenism? Let's start with bin Laden himself.
من قتل حركة بن لادن؟ لنبدأ مع بن لادن نفسه
He probably thought 9/11 was his greatest achievement.
ربما اعتقد أن 9/11 كانت أعظم إنجاز
In reality, it was the beginning of the end for him.
في الواقع، لقد كانت بداية نهايته
He killed 3,000 innocent people, and that filled
فيها قتل 3000 إنسان بريء، و هذا عبأ
the Muslim world with horror and revulsion,
العالم الإسلامي بالرعب و الاشمئزاز
and what that meant was that his idea of jihad
و ما عناه ذلك هو أن فكرته عن الجهاد
could never become mainstream.
لا يمكن أبداً أن تصبح تيار
He condemned himself to operating on the lunatic fringes
لقد أدان نفسه بالعمل في الهوامش الخبولة
of his own community.
في مجتمعه
9/11 didn't empower him; it doomed him.
9/11 لم تقويه، و لكنها قربت حتفه
Who killed bin Ladenism? Abu Musab al-Zarqawi killed it.
من قتل حركة أسامة بن لادن؟ أبو مصعب الزرقاوي قتلها
He was the especially sadistic head of al Qaeda in Iraq
لقد كان هو بشكل خاص الرأس السادية للقاعدة في العراق
who sent hundreds of suicide bombers to attack
الذي أرسل مئات المفجرين الانتحاريين ليهاجموا
not Americans but Iraqis. Muslims. Sunni as well as Shiites.
ليس الأمريكان و لكن العراقيين، مسلمين، سنيين و شيعة
Any claim that al Qaeda had to being protectors of Islam
أي إدعاء ادعته القاعدة بأنها حامية الإسلام
against the Western crusaders
ضد الصليبيين الغربيين
was drowned in the blood of Iraqi Muslims.
غرق في دماء المسلميين العراقيين
Who killed Osama bin Laden? The SEAL Team Six.
من قتل أسامة بن لادن؟ الفرقة سييل 6
Who killed bin Ladenism? Al Jazeera did,
من قتل حركة بن لادن؟ قناة الجزيرة فعلت
Al Jazeera and half a dozen other satellite news stations in Arabic,
الجزيرة و نصف دستة أخرى من القنوات الفضائية الإخبارية العربية
because they circumvented the old, state-owned
لأنها تحايلت على
television stations in a lot of these countries
محطات التلفزيون القديمة و المملوكة من قبل الحكومات في هذه البلاد
which were designed to keep information from people.
و التي أنشئت لحجب المعلومات عن الناس
Al Jazeera brought information to them, showed them
الجزيرة أحضرت المعلومة إليهم، أرتهم بأم أعينهم
what was being said and done in the name of their religion,
ما الذي يقال و يفعل باسم دينهم
exposed the hypocrisy of Osama bin Laden and al Qaeda,
فضحت رياء أسامة بن لادن و القاعدة
and allowed them, gave them the information
و سمحت لهم، أعطتهم المعلومة
that allowed them to come to their own conclusions.
التي سمحت لهم أن يصنعوا استنتاجاتهم الخاصة
Who killed bin Ladenism? The Arab Spring did,
من قتل حركة أسامة بن لادن؟ الربيع العربي فعل
because it showed a way for young Muslims
لأنه فتح الطريق للمسلمين الشباب
to bring about change
ليصنعوا التغيير
in a manner that Osama bin Laden, with his
بطريقة لم يكن أسامة بن لادن
limited imagination, could never have conceived.
بخياله المحدود، لم يكن ليتصورها
Who defeated the global jihad? The American military did,
من هزم الجهاد العالمي؟ الجيش الأمريكي فعل
the American soldiers did, with their allies,
الجنود الأمريكان و حلفائهم
fighting in faraway battlefields.
بالقتال في ساحات المعارك البعيدة
And perhaps, a time will come when they get the rightful credit for it.
و ربما سيأتي وقت سيحصلون فيه على التقدير المناسب لذلك
So all these factors, and many more besides,
إذاً، كل تلك العوامل و الكثير أيضا غيرها
we don't even fully understand some of them yet,
لا يمكننا حتى أن نفهم بعضها بعد
these came together
كلها تفاعلت معاً
to defeat a monstrosity as big as bin Ladenism,
لتهزم بشاعة حركة بن لادن
the global jihad, you needed this group effort.
الجهاد العالمي، احتجنا إلى هذا الجهد الجماعي
Now, not all of these things will work in local jihad.
الآن، لست كل هذه العوامل ستنجح مع الجهاد المحلي
The American military is not going to march into Nigeria
الجيش الأمريكي لن يسير إلى نيجيريا
to take on Boko Haram,
ليهزم بوكو حرام
and it's unlikely that SEAL Team Six will rappel
و ليس من المحتمل أن الفرقة سييل 6 ستهبط
into the homes of al Shabaab's leaders and take them out.
في منازل قادة حركة الشباب و تقضي عليهم
But many of these other factors that were in play
و لكن العديد من هذه العوامل التي لعبت دورا
are now even stronger than before. Half the work is already done.
و الآن حتى أقوى من قبل، نصف العمل قد أنجز
We don't have to reinvent the wheel.
و ليس علينا إعادة اختراع العجلة
The notion of violent jihad in which more Muslims are killed
فكرة الجهاد العنيف حيث يقتل فيه المزيد من المسلمين
than any other kind of people is already thoroughly discredited.
أكثر من أي أناس آخرين فقدت مصداقيتها تماما
We don't have to go back to that.
ليس علينا أن نعود إلى ذلك الوضع
Satellite television and the Internet are informing
القنوات الفضائية و الانترنت تقدم المعلومة
and empowering young Muslims in exciting new ways.
و تدعم المسلمين الشباب بطرق جديدة موجودة
And the Arab Spring has produced governments,
و الربيع العربي أفرز حكومات
many of them Islamist governments,
العديد منها إسلامية
who know that, for their own self-preservation,
من كان ليظن ذلك، لأجل الحفاظ على ذاتها
they need to take on the extremists in their midsts.
تحتاج أن تحذف التطرف من مفاهيمها
We don't need to persuade them, but we do need to help them,
لسنا بحاجة لإقناعهم، و لكنا بحاجة لمساعدتهم
because they haven't really come to this place before.
لأنهم لم يصلوا إلى هذا المكان من قبل
The good news, again, is that a lot of the things they need
الأخبار الجيدة، مجدداً، أن الكثير من الأشياء التي يحتاجونها
we already have, and we are very good at giving:
نحن أصلا نملكها، و نحن معطائين جداً
economic assistance, not just money, but expertise,
المساعدة الاقتصادية، ليس فقط بالمال، و لكن بالخبرة
technology, knowhow,
التكنولوجيا، المعرفة
private investment, fair terms of trade,
الاستثمار في القطاع الخاص، شروط تجارة عادلة
medicine, education, technical support for training
الصحة، التعليم، الدعم التقني للتدريب
for their police forces to become more effective,
لقوات الشرطة لتكون فعالة أكثر
for their anti-terror forces to become more efficient.
لقواتهم المكافحة للإرهاب لتكون فعالة أكثر
We've got plenty of these things.
نحن نملك وفرة في هذه الأشياء
Some of the other things that they need
بعض الأشياء الأخرى التي يحتاجونها
we're not very good at giving. Maybe nobody is.
لا نقدر على منحها، ربما لا أحد يقدر
Time, patience, subtlety, understanding --
الوقت، الصبر، الرقة، التفهم --
these are harder to give.
هذه من الصعب إعطاءها
I live in New York now. Just this week,
أنا أعيش الآن في نيويورك ، فقط بدءاً من هذا الأسبوع
posters have gone up in subway stations in New York
البوسترات غطت محطة قطار الأنفاق في نيويورك
that describe jihad as savage.
تصف الجهاد بالتوحش
But in all the many years that I have covered the Middle East,
لكن خلال الأعوام الماضية جبُت الشرق الأوسط
I have never been as optimistic as I am today
و لم أكن أبداً متفائلاً مثل اليوم
that the gap between the Muslim world and the West
أن الفجوة بين العالم الإسلامي و الغرب
is narrowing fast,
تضيق و بسرعة
and one of the many reasons for my optimism
و واحداً من أسباب هذا التفاؤل
is that, because I know there are millions,
أنني أعلم أن هناك الملايين
hundreds of millions of people, Muslims like that old imam
مئات الملايين من الناس، مسلمين مثل الإمام الشيخ
in Tunis, who are reclaiming this word
في تونس، ممن يطالبون بهذه الكلمة
and restoring to its original, beautiful purpose.
و يستعيدون غرضها الأصلي الجميل
Bin Laden is dead. Bin Ladenism has been defeated.
بن لادن قد مات، حركة بن لادن هزمت
His definition of jihad can now be expunged.
و تعريفه للجهاد يمكن أن يشطب
To that jihad we can say, "Goodbye. Good riddance."
لذلك الجهاد يمكننا أن نقول "وداعا. تخلصنا منك"
To the real jihad we can say, "Welcome back. Good luck."
و للجهاد الحقيقي يمكننا أن نقول "مرحبا بعودتك و حظاً سعيداً"
Thank you. (Applause)
شكراً . (تصفيق)